Personal Information R. Antonio Jose Almeida 55 RCE Porto, 4150-106, Portugal Phone: +351 (91) 408-8698 nunojobpinto@gmail.com

Profile

Software Engineer specialized in NoSQL Document Databases. Major interests are Open-Source, Functional programming, Web, Linux, and NoSQL Document Databases. Currently working with MarkLogic, enabling customers to make a better use of its products and tools.

Professional Experience

MarkLogic, San Carlos, CA, USA

 $Technical\ Enablement\ Engineer$

January 2010

- Technical Instructor: Delivered technical classes about MarkLogic Server to over one hundred students
- Consultant: Discussed customer solutions and MarkLogic features
- Produced technical material used by MarkLogic University
- Direct customer support on early stage prototypes
- MarkLogic Evangelist: NoSQL and open-source communities
- Whitespace-exploration: Created several MarkLogic open-source projects

IBM, Markham, ON, Canada

DB2 Technical Enablement Specialist September 2009 to December 2010

- IBM Go-to-Market programs in Information Management (Information on Demand & Ready for Programs)
- Marketing: Direct customer engagement including technical support
- Ruby on Rails Tech Lead: W3 WebApp for customer & partner engagements
- Operations: Five Ruby on Rails application servers (IBM Internal)
- Lecturer on DB2, pureXML and Ruby on Rails
- Certified DB2 Associate

IBM, Hawthorn, NY, USA

ISV Solutions Engineer - Data Specialist: DB2 pureXML October 2008 to August 2009

- Customer Enablement
- pureXML prototyping and consulting for financial, healthcare and government
- Lecturer on XQuery and SQL/XML for customers and IBM partners
- Co-author and team lead for the DB2 on Rails book
- Cross product integration (Websphere, Tomcat)
- XML Research & Development
- Industry Specific solutions with XML Industry Standards
- Published Technical writer on developerWorks.

Bang & Olufsen, Struer, Denmark

Prototype Developer

July 2008

- Portable stereo prototype design & development
- Requirements analyst
- Multimedia design.

Mobicomp (Microsoft Subsidiary), Braga, Portugal

Software Engineer

October 2006 to March 2007

- C# / VSTO Developer
- Client interface for the companies first ever .NET MobileKeeper Client
- UI Design and HCI Specialist
- Parser for IMC personal data interchange formats (vCard and vCalendar)
- Basic knowledge of XML Industry Standard SyncML.

Triplow, Leça da Palmeira, Portugal

Web Developer

May 2001 to October 2001

- Designer for the Interportas Portal
- Consultant: Custom solutions for client websites

CERTIFICATIONS

IBM Certified Database Associate for DB2, 2009

IBM Information Management DB2 Technical Professional, 2009

EDUCATION

University of Minho, Braga, Portugal

M.S., Computer Science (expected: December 2010)

• Fields of Study: Web applications & Web services, Distributed Systems, XML, Cryptography, Natural Language Processing

B.E., Computer Science and Systems Engineering, March 2008

Engineering College of Aarhus, Aarhus, Denmark

Summer School (Internship) - Bang & Olufsen (B&O) - Erasmus Intensive Program, Conceptual Design and Development of Innovative Products, July 2008

• Fields of Study: Innovation, Product Development and Prototyping

ACTIVITIES

IBM DB2 Student Ambassador

- Featured DB2 Student Ambassador, December 2007
- Founder of the first Portuguese DB2 Students Group, October 2007

Open-Source

- Open-Source Development for the CouchDB Ruby Driver, since March 2008
- Member of the Open Source Support Center, since October 2007
- Several open-source applications hosted at github.com/dscape

TECHNICAL SKILLSET

Database: MarkLogic, MySQL, IBM DB2, CouchDB, SQLite, Oracle, NoSQL, Privacy & Security

XML: XForms, XPath, XSLT, XQuery, XML Schema, SQL/XML, IBM pureXML, Oracle XML DB, XML Industry Standards

Web: HTML, CSS, JavaScript (jQuery), JSON, AJAX, DOM

Ruby: Ruby on Rails, Sinatra, Shoes, ActiveRecord (ORM), DataMapper, ActiveDocument

Java: JDBC, Apache Tomcat, Websphere Aplication Server, Websphere Aplication Server Community Edition

C#: .NET, Visual Studio Tools for Office

Other Languages: Haskell, C, Prolog, Perl, PHP, UNIX Shell Scripting

Developer Tools: TextMate, Eclipse, VIM, Version Control (svn, git), Virtualisation

(VirtualBox, VMware)

Operative Systems: Linux (Redhat, Debian), OS X, Windows

 ${\bf Creative\ Tools:\ Photoshop,\ OpenGL,\ Processing}$